in this video we're going to go over
some physics problems associated with
angular momentum so let's start with
this one
a 10 kilogram disc of radius 3 meters is
spinning at 15 radians per second
what is the inertia of the disc
to calculate the inertia of a disk
here's the equation that you need it's
one half
m r squared
so m is the mass of the disk and r is
the radius
three squared is nine and half of ten is
5 5 times 9 is 45
so the inertia is 45 kilograms
times meter squared
now let's calculate the angular momentum
of the disk
linear momentum is mass times velocity
so angular momentum
is inertia
times omega
so this is the equation that you need to
calculate angular momentum
we have the inertia it's 45
and the angular speed is 15.
so it's 45 times 15
which is 675
and that's it for part b
now let's move on to our second question
the angular momentum of a rod changes
from 15 to 35 kilograms times meter
squared times radians per second in four
seconds
what is the average torque on a rod
now if we think about it we know that
linear momentum is mass in motion
anything that's moving has momentum
well angular momentum is very similar
but for objects that it's spinning any
object that rotates or spins has angular
momentum
now to calculate the net force
acted on an object
you can use this equation it's equal to
the change in momentum divided by the
change in time
so similarly if we wish to calculate the
net torque
it's equal to the change in the angular
momentum divided by the change in time
now both equations can come from
newton's second law this comes from
newton's second law of motion
which states that the net force acting
on an object
is the mass times the acceleration
and this expression comes from newton's
second law as it relates to rotational
motion
which states that the net torque acting
on an object
is equal to the inertia of the object
times the angular acceleration
angular acceleration is the change
in the angular velocity divided by the
change in time
and momentum is inertia
times omega
so the change in momentum that is the
change in angular momentum is the
inertia
times the change in angular velocity
so therefore we can replace i times
delta w
with delta l
so that's we have this expression the
net torque is equal to the change
and the angular momentum of a system
divided by the change in time
so now let's go ahead and calculate the
average net torque used in that equation
so it's equal to the change in angular
momentum
which is the difference between those
two numbers that's 35 minus 15
divided by the change in time
so the change in angular momentum is 20
and if we divide that by four
we'll get the average net torque which
is five
newtons times meters
so this is the answer
so because the angle momentum is
increasing
the net torque acting on the system is
positive
if l was decreasing
then the net torque acting on system
will be negative
number three a force of 300 newtons acts
on a 2.5 meter long rod initially at
rest as shown in a picture below
what is the torque acting on the rod
the torque
is the force
times the lever arm
the force is 300 newtons
and the lever arm or the moment arm
is 2.5 meters
so 300 times 2.5
that's 750.
so the torque is 750
newtons times meters
now let's move on to part b
what is the final angular momentum of
the rod if the force acts on it for
eight seconds
now the torque acting on the system the
net torque is equal to the change in the
angle momentum of the system
divided by the change in time
so if we multiply both sides by delta t
the torque multiplied by time
is equal to the final momentum minus the
initial angular momentum
now the rod was initially at rest
so the initial angle momentum is zero
so therefore to calculate the final
angular momentum it's simply the torque
multiplied by the time
so it's going to be 750
times
a time value of 8 seconds
so the final angular momentum
is 6000
units
now let's move on to part c
what is the final angular speed of the
rod
now keep in mind angular momentum
is equal to inertia
times angular velocity or angle speed
so since we have the final angular
momentum we could calculate the final
angular speed
however we do need to calculate the
inertia
of the rod first
so for a rod where the axis of rotation
is at the end of the rod
the inertia
is 1 3
ml squared
so m is the mass of the rod
which
i did not give you for some reason so
let me do that now let's say the mass of
the rod is 10 kilograms
and l
is
the length of the rod so that l is not
the same as the angular momentum l so
the length of the rod is 2.5
so 2.5 squared
times 10
divided by 3
is 20.83
so that's the inertia of the system
so to calculate the final speed we need
to take the final angular momentum and
divided by the inertia
so that's 6000 divided by 20.833
and so the final angular speed is going
to be about 288
radians per second
so now let's calculate how much work was
done by the force
and we're going to do it two ways
so you may want to write down the
numbers that you see here because
i need to erase
all the stuff that's here
so the first way in which we can
calculate the work done
is by calculating the change in
rotational kinetic energy of the object
now the initial kinetic energy is zero
so therefore the work is equal to the
final rotational kinetic energy
and the equation for rotational kinetic
energy is one-half
inertia times omega squared
so the inertia of the object
was 20.83
and it's really 0.83 repeating
the final angular speed
was 288 radians per second and let's not
forget to square it
so this will give you if you rounded to
nearest thousand is 864 000
joules
so that's how much work was done by the
force
to accelerate it to a speed of 288
ratings per second
the second way to get it is to use this
equation
work is equal to the rotational torque
multiplied by the angular displacement
the angular displacement you can
calculate it from this equation is one
half
the initial plus the final angular speed
multiplied by the time
so the torque we said was 750
the initial angular speed is zero
the final angular speed is 288
and the time was 8 seconds
so half of 288 is 144.
so that's the average angular speed
so it's 750 times 144 times 8
which will give you the same answer of
864 000 joules
so as you can see there's multiple ways
in which you can calculate the work done
number four
so we have a 500 kilogram merry-go-round
with a radius of 10 meters and it's
moving at a speed of 0.5 radians per
second
a child jumps on it four meters away
from
the central axis of rotation what is the
inertia of the merry-go-round and then
let's find the inertia of the child
so let's say this is the merry-go-round
and this is the central axis of rotation
so here's the center
it has a radius
of 10 meters
and the mass
is 500 kilograms
so we can treat the merry-go-round as a
disc and the inertia of a disc
is one-half
mr squared
so that's going to be one-half
times the mass of 500
times the radius of
10. so 10 squared is 100 times 500
times 0.5
so the inertia of the
merry-go-round is 25 000
kilograms times meter squared now part b
we need to calculate the inertia of the
child on the merry-go-round
so here's the child
the child is four meters
away
from the center rotation
now the inertia of the child
is going to be m r squared
it's not one half m r squared
because the mass of the child is all
concentrated at that point
whereas the mass of the disc
is uniformly distributed throughout this
whole
circle
so the inertia of the child could be the
mass which is 50 or rather 40 kilograms
multiplied by the radius of 4
squared that's how far the child is away
from the axis of rotation
so the inertia of the child is only 640.
so now how can we use that information
to calculate the final speed of the
merry-go-round
now what you need to know is that the
momentum of the system will be conserved
the angular momentum of the system will
not change unless there's a net torque
acting on it
so if the child jumps
on a merry-go-round
say if the child jumps straight down
the child will not exert a torque on
the mega round and so the total momentum
will have to be the same
so the initial angular momentum must be
equal to the final angular momentum
so that is the inertia
of the merry-go-round
times the initial speed of the
merry-go-round
is equal to
the inertia of the child plus the
merry-go-round times the final speed
so the inertia of the merry-go-round
that's 25 000.
the initial angular speed is 0.5 radians
per second
now the inertia of the merry-go-round
plus the child
is 25 000 plus the 640 so it's 25640
times the final angle speed
so to calculate the final angular speed
it's going to be 25 thousand
times point five divided by twenty five
thousand six forty
so the final angular speed is
point
four
eight eight
radians per second
so let's talk about what's going on here
when the child jumps on the
merry-go-round
the inertia
of the whole system increases
and when the inertia increases
the angular speed has to decrease
so that the momentum of the system
specifically the angular momentum
is conserved and that's what's happening
so whenever the child jumps on a
merry-go-round the speed of the
merry-go-round decreases slightly
if the child were to jump off the mergle
route the inertia would decrease
and the angler speed of
the mergo round would increase again
so the angle momentum must be conserved
if there is no net torque
another example that illustrates this is
imagine if you have a skater
and let's say the skater
has her arm stretched out
and at the same time she's spinning
let's say she's spinning at a rate of
two radians per second
and let's say her inertia i'm just going
to pick up a number let's say it's 10.
so her angle momentum is 10 times 2 is
20.
now let's say if she brings her arms
close
to her body so let's say i'm just going
to draw a picture
what do you think is going to happen to
her angler speed
while she's spinning and she brings her
arms closer to her body
by moving her arms closer to her body
the inertia changes
her inertia decreases
inertia may now be let's say five
so therefore
if she decreases the inertia her angular
speed has to increase
so if the inertia reduces by a factor of
two
the angular speed will increase by a
factor of two so it's going to be four
beats per second
such that momentum
is still 20.
so she's going to be spinning a lot
faster
and so that's another example of the
conservation of angular momentum
angle momentum is always conserved
when the net torque acting on a system
meaning an external torque is zero
you